-= CHD字幕組 =-  字幕製作：janboor@CHD
The Oracle's words stand as a warning.
先知早就發出警語
A prophecy.
一個預言
Sparta will fall.
斯巴達會殞落
All of Greece will fall.
希臘也會全軍覆滅
And Persian fire will reduce Athens to cinder.
波斯烈焰會將雅典城燒成灰燼
For Athens is a pile of stone and wood...
畢竟雅典只是由木石…
...and cloth and dust...
及塵土搭建
...and, as dust, will vanish into the wind.
而塵土終將灰飛煙滅
Only the Athenians themselves exist.
最終留下的只有雅典人民
And the fate of the world hangs  on their every syllable.
世界的命運  懸在雅典議會的最終決議
Only the Athenians exist.
最終留下的只有雅典人
And only stout wooden ships can save them.
唯有強健的艦隊才能拯救他們
Wooden ships...
木製的軍艦
...and a tidal wave of heroes' blood.
還有英雄熱血捲起的驚濤駭浪
片名：300壯士：帝國崛起
Leonidas, my husband...
我的先夫雷奧尼達
...Leonidas, your king...
你們的國王雷奧尼達
...Leonidas and the brave 300 are dead.
他和三百壯士已壯烈犧牲
The free men and women of Greece...
希臘的自由人民
...are not bound by  a beautiful Spartan death.
不覺得有義務替他們復仇
War is not their love.
他們不熱衷征戰
Yet he lay down his life for them.
而他卻自願為他們犧牲
For the promise Greece holds.
只為了希臘承諾的遠景
'Tis our enemies who forged our freedom  in the fires of war.
敵人的戰火將促使我們爭取自由
It was King Darius  who came to take our land.
大流士國王前來巧取豪奪
Ten years ago,  when youth still burned in our eyes...
在十年前，當我們仍年輕氣盛
...before this bitter war forced our children  to become men.
在殘酷戰爭迫使男孩快速成熟前
Ten years ago, this war began...
十年前，這場戰爭展開
...as all wars begin:
如同其他戰爭的開端
With a grievance.
由嫌隙挑起
Marathon.
馬拉松之戰
The Persian king, Darius...
波斯國王大流士
...annoyed by the notion of Greek freedom...
視自由的希臘城邦為眼中釘
...has come to Greece to bring us to heel.
決定揮兵征服希臘
He makes landfall at the field of Marathon...
他的艦隊在馬拉松平原登陸
...with an invading force  which outnumbers...
以三比一懸殊兵力
...the Greek defenders three-to-one.
直逼希臘聯軍
And so at dawn, the hopeless Athenians  do the unthinkable.
黎明時，雅典人決意背水一戰
They attack.
他們發動攻勢
They attack the weary Persians  as they disembark...
就在疲憊的兵團歷經整月航程
...their ships  on shaky legs after a month at sea.
步履蹣跚下船時襲擊
They attack before they can  establish their war camp...
他們在波斯大軍開始紮營  和補給軍備前
...and supply their soldiers.
就展開攻勢
And who...
是誰…
...is the architect of this mad strategy?
策劃出此種瘋狂攻略？
A little-known Athenian...
一位名不見經傳的…
...soldier.
雅典士兵
His men call him...
他的弟兄們叫他…
...Themistokles.
帝米斯托克力
He gives the Persians a taste  of Athenian shock combat.
他用雅典威嚇戰術款待波斯大軍
All thoughts of glory are gone.
此時榮譽的念頭已褪去
Thousands dead.
敵方死傷數千
Hundreds of them their own.
雅典也折損數百人命
A free Greece...
一切只為了希臘自由的信念
...an Athenian experiment  called "democracy. "
這個由雅典人發起  名為「民主」的實驗
Could this idea be worth it?
為這個信念犧牲值得嗎？
Worth all this sacrifice?
所有的死傷和苦難
Themistokles would let  the good King Darius decide.
帝米斯托克力讓大流士國王決定
For through the chaos...
突然在兵荒馬亂中
...a moment appeared.
一個契機浮現
And Themistokles would seize it.
帝米斯托克力決定機不可失
A moment...
這一刻…
...that would ring across the centuries.
在歷史中將永被傳頌
A moment that would...
這一刻…
...raise him from simple soldier...
會讓他從平凡士兵
...to the height of Athenian political power.
晉陞雅典政治權力頂端
No!
不
A moment that would make  Themistokles a legend.
這一刻帝米斯托克力化為傳奇
Yet even as the praise and glory...
即便此舉…
...were heaped upon him...
讓他備享尊榮擁戴
Themistokles knew in his heart  he had made a mistake.
帝米斯托克力心知他鑄下大錯
It was Darius' son, Xerxes...
他在大流士之子薛西斯眼中
...whose eyes had the stink  of destiny about them.
看到未來命運的不祥徵兆
Themistokles knew  he should have killed that boy.
帝米斯托克力知道他該殺了王子
That glorious mistake  would forever haunt him.
這滔天大錯日後勢必釀成大禍
And so it was Themistokles himself...
帝米斯托克力…
...who sent a ripple  across the Persian empire...
不僅讓波斯帝國首度吃了敗仗
...and set into motion...
也讓帝國決心捲土重來
...forces that would bring fire  to the heart of Greece.
日後再度直取希臘中心
For as the good king lay dying...
大流士國王重傷命危
...all his greatest generals...
所有將軍重臣…
...and advisors  were summoned to his bedside.
都被召喚前來
None greater...
其中最位高權重的…
...than his finest  naval commander, Artemisia.
就屬海軍統帥雅特米西亞
Her ferocity bested only by her beauty.
她的殘暴  與她的美艷程度不相上下
Her beauty matched only  by her devotion to her king.
而她的美貌只有  對國王的死忠程度能比擬
Darius favored Arfemisia  among his generals...
大流士偏愛雅特米西亞
...for she had brought him victory  on the battlefield.
因為她戰功彪炳
In her...
她是他眼中…
...he had the perfect warrior protegee...
完美的軍事神童
...that his son, Xerxes, would never be.
那是薛西斯王子永遠無法比擬的
So sweet, my child.
我甜美的孩子
My sweet...
我甜美的…
...child.
孩子
Father.
父王
Xerxes.
薛西斯
Do not repeat your father's mistake.
不要重複父王的錯誤
Leave the ignoble Greeks to their ways.
讓那些低劣的希臘人去吧
Only the gods can defeat them.
只有諸神能擊敗他們
Only the gods.
只有諸神
For seven days, Xerxes mourned...
薛西斯足足哀悼了七天
paralyzed by grief.
被哀傷徹底擊垮
On the eighth day, Artemisia  whispered the seed of madness...
第八日，雅特米西亞埋下  從此將吞噬他的…
...that would consume him.
瘋狂種子
Your father's words were not a warning...
你父王的話不是對你的警語
...but a challenge.
而是對你的挑戰
Only the gods can defeat the Greeks?
只有諸神能擊敗希臘人？
You will be a god-king.
你會成為神王
Artemisia gathered the priests, wizards...
雅特米西亞結集帝國內…
...and mystics  from every corner of the empire.
所有祭司、巫師和秘宗
They wrapped”
他們用浸了…
...the young king in Cimmerian gauze  dipped in ancient potions...
古老丹藥的  西米裏紗布包裹年輕國王
...and set him to wander the desert...
送他去沙漠裏遊蕩
...till in a delirium of heat and thirst,  he stumbled upon...
當他因高溫和脫水神智不清時  無意間去到…
...a hermit's cave.
一群隱士的洞穴
Xerxes passed the vacant eyes...
薛西斯穿過這些  空洞的眼神…
...and empty souls...
和靈魂
...of the hollow creatures that dwell  in the dark corners of all men's hearts.
這群虛無的怪物  潛匿在人世間最黑暗的角落
And in that darkness...
在黑暗虛無中
...he surrendered himself completely...
他將全部的自己…
...to power so evil and perverse...
奉獻給邪惡的黑暗勢力
...that, as he emerged...
當他再度浮現時
...no part of a human man  that was Xerxes survived.
薛西斯過往的人性完全被抹滅
His eyes blazed like scarlet coals.
他的雙眼像炭火般猩紅閃耀
He was stripped, cleansed, glabrous...
他被淘空洗淨…
...and smooth.
光滑平順
Xerxes was reborn...
薛西斯轉生為…
...a god.
邪神
Artemisia trusted no one.
雅特米西亞不相信任何人
So in the cover of night...
藉著夜慕的掩護
...the palace was cleansed  of all Xerxes' allies.
皇宮內所有薛西斯親信都被剷除
All those he trusted...
那些他信任過的
...all those who had raised him...
那些撫育過他的
...all those he had  once looked to for counsel...
那些他曾徵詢採納過意見的
...were quickly introduced to her wrath.
都慘遭她毒手
And as the god-king stood...
當神王終於…
...before his people...
現身子民前時
...Anemisia watched her flawless  manipulation take shape.
雅特米西亞  精心操縱的計劃終於體現
- For glory's sake...  - For glory's sake...
為榮耀之名
-...for vengeance's sake...  -...for vengeance's sake...
以復仇之名
...war.
開戰
---War!
War is coming to Greece...
戰爭即將席捲希臘
...in the visage of a monster army  over a million strong.
面臨軍容壯盛的百萬大軍
It should be little more than a formality  for Themistokles...
理所當然應由馬拉松之戰的英雄
...the hero of Marathon...
帝米斯托克力
...to finish what he began.
來了結他挑起的恩怨
Please! We must appeal to Xerxes' reason!
各位  我們得跟薛西斯理性協商
Coward!
懦夫
Athens is a city of cowards!
雅典城全是懦夫
Shut your cock hole!
閉上你的鳥嘴
Shut your own!
你也是
I'll kill you! Fuck the Spartans!
我要殺了你，去他的斯巴達人
Fuck those muscle-bound boy-lovers!
叫那些愛跟男人鬼混的莽夫去死
Silence!
安靜
Silence for the hero of Marathon!
讓馬拉松英雄說話
This is a democracy, not a street fight.
這裏講求的是民主  不是街頭混戰
Quiet! It's Themistokles.
安靜，聽帝米斯托克力的
The Persian attack will come  from both the north and the south.
波斯大軍會從南北夾擊分批進攻
The city-states should negotiate a truce.
城邦該試圖協商求和
Yes, yes, we must negotiate.
對，對，我們得談判
Negotiate with tyranny?
跟這個暴君談判？
Give me one example of when  that has ever profited a nation.
歷史上有哪個國家因此得利
- You're right. We must unite.  - My fellow countrymen...
說得對，我們得團結起來  我的同胞
...we can only judge the future...
我們只能從歷史的教訓…
...from what we have suffered in the past.
推斷未來
Now, many of you here  stood with me at Marathon.
你們許多人曾在馬拉松  與我並肩奮戰
And for those of you who served...
那些曾在戰爭血腥殘暴中…
...and faced the cut  and thrust of battle...
存活下來的人
...you know how true peace is forged.
知道真正的和平是如何得來的
Do not be deceived.
別被愚弄了
Xerxes, the son of Darius...
大流士之子薛西斯…
...is a wolf at our door.
絕非善類
Right here, right now...
此時此刻
...we must choose:
我們必須選擇
Do we stand and fight for Greece or not?
是否要起身捍衛希臘
Argos...
阿哥斯
...Corinth...
哥林斯
...Megara...
梅加拉
...Athens.
雅典
Not even Sparta  can match the Persians alone.
即便斯巴達都無法單挑波斯大軍
We must persevere as one nation.
我們得聯合禦敵方纔能存活
Or we will perish clinging onto...
不然只能抱著…
...our own self-interests.
私利滅亡
Send us the ships that we need  to defend Greece.
提供我們足以防禦希臘的艦隊
Themistokles will need more  than our cities' ships.
帝米斯托克力不止需要  各城邦的船艦
He will need our children  to join the fight.
他會要求送所有孩子上戰場
And what of Sparta?
那斯巴達呢？
You send every ship that we have...
你們負責結集城邦所有船艦…
...to the northern coast of Euboea.
到優卑亞北岸
I will go and seek the help  of the great Spartans.
我會去尋求偉大斯巴達人的協助
Still no word...
你差往…
...from the messenger  you sent to Sparta.
斯巴達的特使仍沒回音
King Leonidas may have been insulted  by your generous offer.
雷奧尼達國王或許  被你慷慨的條件激怒了
Perhaps I need to march into Sparta myself  and burn it to the ground.
也許我該揮軍斯巴達  將它燒為灰燼
Remember...
別忘了
...when a king is loved as I am...
像我這般備受愛戴的國王
...much can be accomplished.
可完成許多大業
They would be fools  to resist my divine power.
若試圖抵抗我的天賦神權  就太愚蠢了
Athens is attempting to assemble a coalition.
雅典正在努力聯合其他城邦
It'll be nothing more  than a patchwork of ships.
就算成功也只是堆拼湊的破船
Once these waters have been traversed,  I will lead my force across the land.
一旦橫渡海洋，我會朝陸路推進
I will remind the cowards of Greece...
好提醒那些希臘懦夫
...that we have not forgotten their insolence.
我們沒有忘記他們的傲慢行徑
Rest and water the horses.
休息一下，讓馬匹飲水
It's best I go alone.
我最好單獨前往
Spartans don't get along well with others.
斯巴達人不喜與外族往來
- Spartans.  - Themistokles.
- 斯巴達人  - 帝米斯托克力
You old snake.
你這隻老狐貍
- What brings you this far south?  - I've come to see Leonidas.
- 何事讓你遠行南下？  - 來警告雷奧尼達
- To warn him that the Persians are on the march.  - You're too late.
- 波斯人來犯  - 你來遲了
Persian messenger already presented  his terms to Leonidas.
波斯特使已將招降條件  呈給雷奧尼達
Symbolic offering of earth and water.
象徵性供上土地和水源
Spartans!
斯巴達人
Know this and know it well.
謹記這點
That any Spartan's finest moment...
斯巴達人最至高無上的一刻
...the greatest fulfillment...
生命中最摯愛…
...of all he holds dear...
和最大的成就
...is that moment...
就是當你們…
...when he has fought his heart out...
為了保存斯巴達文化
...for the preservation of Sparta...
而窮盡全力奮戰
...and lies dead on the battlefield...
進而戰死沙場
...victorious.
取得勝利
Now...
現在
...who is willing to die at our king's side?  Ah-ooh!
誰願意與吾王一同赴死？
Ah-ooh! Ah-ooh!
Themistokles.
帝米斯托克力
You've come a long way to stroke your cock  whilst watching real men train.
你大老遠來就為了邊納涼  邊看真男人鍛煉嗎？
Queen Gorgo.
歌果王后
Shouldn't he be training them  to live at their king's side?
他不該訓練孩子為國王捨命吧？
A new age is dawning, Gorgo.
新時代已來臨，歌果
Won't be long before men rise up  and shed the yoke of mysticism and tyranny.
不久後，人們將起身  推翻神秘信仰和暴君
- That sounds like a threat.  - No.
- 聽起來像是威脅  - 不是
An opportunity to join the rest of free Greece  and stand against a true tyrant.
我邀請你們加入自由希臘城邦  共同抵抗暴君
Unless, of course, you and Leonidas  have already made a deal with Xerxes.
除非你和雷奧尼達  已和薛西斯達成協議
No terms were reached.
我們沒能達成共識
Xerxes' messenger was...
薛西斯的特使很…
Well, he was rude and he lacked respect.
他很無禮並出言不遜
He didn't understand the same threats made  in Thebes and Athens would not work here.
他不瞭解恐嚇底比斯  和雅典的手法，在這並不管用
This is the birthplace  of the world's greatest warriors.
這裏是世上最偉大戰士的誕生地
Men whose king would stand  and fight and die for any one of them.
國王和戰士並肩作戰，為彼此犧牲
Xerxes' messenger...
薛西斯特使…
...did not understand  this is no typical Greek city-state.
不瞭解  這裏不是一般的希臘城邦
This is Sparta.
這裏是斯巴達
It was clear to the messenger  there'd be no Spartan submission?
所以特使瞭解斯巴達不歸順？
It was clear.
非常清楚
Even now Leonidas is in counsel  with the Oracle over his battle plan.
此刻雷奧尼達正與先知  討論作戰計劃
The Festival of the Carneia  is all that stands in our way.
唯一出兵的阻礙是喀尼雅節
Surely the Oracle will see we must fight.
先知當然瞭解我們非戰不可
Well, then my timing is perfect.
那我來對時機了
I am commanding a fleet of ships  that will represent a united Greece.
我將率領代表聯合希臘的艦隊
I need Sparta to join me.
我需要斯巴達的加入
Give me your ships, Gorgo.
把艦隊交給我吧，歌果
I'll make sure that Xerxes wishes  he never crossed the Aegean.
我會讓薛西斯後悔渡過愛琴海
You'll receive no Spartan ships.  We've no interest in a united Greece.
斯巴達的艦隊不會加入  我們對統一希臘沒有興趣
That is your dream, Themistokles, not ours.
那是你的夢想，帝米斯托克力  不是我們的
All I am concerned with  is the preservation...
我只在乎斯巴達的…
...of Sparta.
存亡
My guards will see you out.
我的侍衛會護送你離開
It's funny that you mock freedom...
你們嘲諷自由…
...here in your selfish isolation.
及自私鎖國的行徑真可笑
Yet freedom, in her wisdom...
因為冥冥之中
...has chosen you to defend her.
上天選擇你們捍衛自由
MY queen.
我的王后
Will Sparta join our fight?
斯巴達會加入我軍嗎？
Apparently the Persians have offered  the Spartans something they cannot refuse.
顯然波斯為斯巴達帶來  他們無法抗拒的誘惑
And what is that?
那是什麼？
A beautiful death.
壯烈犧牲的機會
They say you are the bravest  of our captives.
大家都說你是戰俘裏最英勇的
They say you are a whore  from the eastern seas.
大家都說你是來自東海的娼妓
You're not the smartest.
卻不是最聰明的
Your commander is a Greek.
你們的統帥是希臘人
Just like me.
跟我一樣
You Persian men take your orders  from a Greek woman.
一群波斯男人任由希臘娘們使喚
Yes, my brother, I am Greek by birth...
是的兄弟，我的確生為希臘人
...and I have Greek blood  running through my veins.
體內也流著希臘血液
But my heart...
但我的心
...is Persian.
屬於波斯
Within hours...
數小時內
...the Greek fleet will be shattered.
希臘艦隊就會被瓦解
What of our master  and the much-feared Spartans?
那我們主子  和人人敬畏的斯巴達人呢？
There's nothing to fear.
沒什麼好怕的
Only King Leonidas  and his personal guard of 300...
只有雷奧尼達國王和  他三百名貼身侍衛…
...have marched to fight.
- 前來應戰  - 他們會立刻…
They'll collapse. Instantly.
被殲滅
You.
你
Do you agree?
你同意嗎？
Many will perish.
會死傷慘重
Your confidence leaves me  with a strong impression.
你的信心讓我驚艷
It's a curious thing for a simple ship guard...
卑微船員被我問話
...to not lower his eyes  when questioned by me.
而不低頭還真罕見
That could've been just a lack of discipline.
這可被解讀為缺乏紀律
But a man's hands do not lie.
但男人的雙手不會說謊
They can reveal...
它們會揭露…
...every imperfection  and flaw in his character.
主人的破綻和缺陷
You see, your hands  are not rough enough...
你的手對船上粗活來說…
...to work the rigging of this ship.
不夠粗糙
I know every single man beneath my lash.
我麾下每個人我都認識
Can you explain to me  how I don't know you?
你能解釋我為何不認識你嗎？
Forgive me, commander.
原諒我，統帥
Let me introduce myself.
請容我自我介紹
Seize the spy.
拿下奸細
Coward.
懦夫
Storm is upon us.
暴風雨來襲了
It's just some mad Greek weather.
典型的希臘爛天氣
- Themistokles.  - Come.
- 帝米斯托克力  - 進來
Calisto.
克裏斯托
What is spoken here must not be repeated.
這房裏的對話不可外傳
Anywhere.
誰都不能說
My son has not earned the right  to sit at the table of combat veterans.
小犬還不配跟身經百戰的將士  平起平坐
- But you can trust him.  - Very well.
- 但你可以相信他  - 很好
- Tell me.  - A Greek woman...
- 告訴我  - 波斯南下艦隊…
...commands all of Xerxes' ships  to the south.
由一名女子統帥
Artemisia.
雅特米西亞
I know of her.
我聽說過她
Artemisia is murderous by trade  with true skill on the sea...
雅特米西亞是嫻熟的殺手  也深諳水性
...and she has thirst for vengeance.
她一心渴望復仇
Rumors are her entire family...
傳聞她全家…
...was murdered  by a squad of Greek hoplites.
慘遭希臘民兵殺害
I have heard all the stories.
我聽說過那些故事
And the hoplites spared no one on that day.
那天民兵肆虐，無人生還
The story goes  that they raped and murdered...
據說她全家…
...her entire family.
慘遭強姦殺害
And then they turned their attention  towards her.
之後她也慘遭毒手
After years of being kept in the bowels  of a Greek slave ship...
被囚禁在希臘奴隸船艙多年後
...she was discarded and left for dead...
她被棄置，任其自生自滅
...where she was found near death  by a Persian emissary.
她在瀕死邊緣被波斯特使救起
Artemisia vowed that day  to return to Greece...
雅特米西亞發誓當她返回希臘時
...only when she could watch it burn.
定要將它燒為灰燼
She was fed, clothed, trained  by the finest warriors of the Persian empire...
她被波斯帝國  最精銳戰士養育和訓練
...until no match could be found...
直到她的劍術…
...for her skills and gift with the sword.
所向無敵
The great King Darius was impressed  by her commitment.
大流士深為她的毅力所折服
And she quickly rose to command  at his side.
她快速晉陞高位，隨侍在側
She has sold her soul...
她已將靈魂…
...to Death himself.
出賣給死神
Well, some could say  that I've sold mine to Greece.
有些人也說我將靈魂賣給希臘
And what do you think?
你怎麼看？
- Me?  - Yes.
- 我？  - 對
You are the future of this country.
你是國家的未來棟樑
I'm ready to fight.
我準備好作戰了
I like him. He reminds me of you.
我喜歡他，他很像你
We will need...
我們需要…
...every last man.
所有男丁
He is still just a boy.
他還是個孩子
Much younger...
很多人比我年輕…
-...have defended our country.  - Enough!
- 都挺身報國  - 夠了
You are a dreamer  and will speak of this no more.
你只會做白日夢，不准再提了
Themistokles, I've set your plan in motion.
帝米斯托克力  我已將你的計劃付諸實行
And my land force  will be assembled by the second day.
我的陸軍第二天就會結集完成
You will be needed.  I can assure you of that.
到時會需要你們支援  我可以保證這點
And there is bad news.
還有則壞消息
Leonidas has marched north  to the Hot Gates.
雷奧尼達已出兵北上溫泉關
Bad news? With the Spartans...
壞消息？有斯巴達…
- ...at the Hot Gates, our victory is assured.  - If the army were with him.
- 鎮守溫泉關，我們必勝無疑  - 若他率領大軍肯定如此
But between the Oracle and the Carneia...
但因先知和喀尼雅節
...Leonidas has marched to Thermopylae  with just 300 men.
雷奧尼達只帶領三百壯士  前往溫泉關
So the only thing standing between Athens...
所以介於雅典和徹底滅亡…
...and total annihilation...
的命運之間
...is Leonidas and 300 Spartans.
只有雷奧尼達  和斯巴達三百壯士
I will search out the veterans among them.
我會找出有作戰經驗的人
- Establish some order among the volunteers.  - Good.
- 在志願兵間建立起秩序  - 很好
There's little time  to teach these farmhands strategy.
沒時間教這些農夫戰術了
Just keep them well fed...
盡量讓他們吃飽
...and sober.
別讓他們喝醉
Anything else?
還有呢？
Wouldn't hurt if they could  swing a sword.
能教會他們用劍也不錯
Well, I'll be damned.
不是吧
Shit.
糟了
- Does your father know that you're here?  - No, sir.
- 你父親知道嗎？  - 不，大人
And this shield and sword?
這盾牌和劍哪來的？
My grandfather's.
我外公的
My mother entrusted them to me  this morning.
我母親今早將它們托付給我
- When she gave you her blessing?  - Yes, sir.
- 當她為你祈福時？  - 是的，大人
With a sharp blade, no less.
她還替你把劍磨了
Your father is preparing a surprise  for our enemy tomorrow.
你父親正在準備  明天要給敵人的驚喜
I choose to fight here. Now.
我選擇在這裏作戰  此時此刻
Come aboard my ship.
登上我的船艦
That is where you will fight.
你在那裏迎敵
Yes, sir.
是的，大人
We've just over 50 ships.
我們只有五十幾艘船
Persian forces reported a number  in the thousands.
據報波斯大軍有上千艘
- Those ships appear hardly seaworthy.  - Nothing like the monster ships...
- 我們的船看起來不堪一擊  - 跟波斯艦隊的龐然大物無法比
-...of the Persian fleet.  - We have the advantage. Speed, maneuverability.
如此一來，我們的速度  和敏捷度都佔了上風
The rest of the city-states have sent  anywhere from a handful to a single ship.
其他城邦分別派來一到數艘船
- Of course, Athens supplied the balance.  - We have report...
- 然後由雅典來補足數量  - 我們收到消息
...a small advance force of Persian ships have  taken refuge from the storm across the strait.
一支波斯小型先遣艦隊  在海峽對面躲避暴風雨
If the weather breaks,  we could hit them at dawn.
若天氣好轉，我們可在黎明突襲
An early Greek victory.
提早迎來希臘捷報
The gods have given us an opportunity...
諸神給我們機會…
...to wound the Persians,  strengthen Greek morale.
挫傷波斯大軍  提升希臘士氣
A tempting distraction.
聽起來很誘人
But we'll stick to the battle plan.
但我們按原定作戰計劃
Today at sundown, we will sail out  to meet the main Persian fleet.
今天落日時，我們出航  迎戰波斯主力艦隊
We'll attack in the open water  with no shore to narrow the battle.
在開闊海域上  讓他們無法拉短戰線
To attack a force of over 1000 ships...
用微小的艦隊去襲擊…
...with our meager force is suicide.
上千艘船簡直是自殺
Such is my plan.
我的計劃正是如此
Look at their excuse for a navy.
他們的海軍真是太可笑了
Their ships are of little threat.
那些船艦完全不具威脅
I need a second in command, Artaphernes.
我需要副手，阿爾塔費尼斯
And whoever proves their excellence  will earn a place beside me.
只要能證明自己能力  便可在我身邊當左右手
General Bandari has offered  to lead the first attack.
班德瑞將軍自願帶領首波攻勢
Bandafi.
班德端
Commander.
統帥
If I let you lead our first offensive...
若讓你率領首波攻勢
...what guarantee do I have  that you'll bring me a quick victory?
你如何擔保我方快速致勝？
My word and my life.
我的承諾和性命
Good.
很好
My rules of engagement?
我的交戰守則是？
Humiliate the Greeks  and lay waste to their tiny ships.
羞辱希臘人，摧毀所有船艦
They'll be dead to the last man.
他們會全軍覆沒
My brothers.
我的弟兄們
Steady your hearts.
靜下心來
Look deep into your souls.
深切反思內心
For your mettle is to be tested this day.
今日你將面臨最大試煉
If in the heat of battle...
若在戰火延燒中
you need a reason to fight on...
你需要繼續作戰的理由
...an idea for which you will give up...
一個你願為其…
...all that you will ever have...
犧牲一切的理由
...you need only to look at the man  who fights at your side.
只需環顧和你並肩作戰的兄弟
This is the "why" of battle.
這就是作戰的理由
This is the brotherhood of men-at-arms.
這就是軍人讓的敵血盟約
An unbreakable bond...
一個堅不可摧的連結
...made stronger by the crucible of combat.
歷經嚴峻考驗而益發強壯
You will never be closer than with those  who you shed your blood with.
再不會有比浴血兄弟更深的情誼
For there is no nobler cause...
再也沒有比…
...than to fight for those  who will la y down their life for you.
為同生共死的弟兄奮戰  更高貴的目標
So you fight strong today.
所以今日務必堅韌不懈
You fight for your brothers.
為你的弟兄而戰
Fight for your families.
為你的家人而戰
Most of all, you fight for Greece!
更重要的是，為希臘而戰
Greece!
希臘
Yeah!
對
And there is only one thing to make sure of  when the fighting starts.
開戰後只需確保一件事
What's that?
什麼事？
Don't get killed on the first day.
別在第一天陣亡
That goes for the rest of you.
你們都一樣
Persian ships...
波斯…
...are strong at the front.
船艦的船頭堅固
But they are weak...
但中段…
...in the middle.
脆弱
We attack them there.
我們就攻擊那裏
NOW!
預備
Attack!
攻擊
Ram them!
撞擊他們
Archers, now! Now!
弓箭手，放箭，放箭
Reverse!
後退
NOW!
現在
Go through them!
撞斷他們
The enemy's tactics...
敵軍的戰術…
...are creative.
真有創意
The defensive circle  leaves no front to assault.
環狀防線讓我們無法攻擊
We are losing.
我們節節敗退
No, you are losing.
不，是你節節敗退
Pull back.
撒退
Let them have this day.
今天算賞他們甜頭
I'm bored with your failures, Bandari.
你的失敗讓我厭煩，班德瑞
I'll not let this wound slow me.
我不會讓這點小傷阻礙我
Heh. Somehow I believe you.
我相信你
My blade will be sharp and ready  by the morning.
我明早就會把劍磨利準備就緒
Good. Tomorrow you will fight  alongside your father.
很好，你將和你父親並肩作戰
Not bad...
對一群農夫來說…
-...for a bunch of farmers.  - And poets and sculptors.
- 還不賴  - 還有詩人和雕塑家
Who'd have known untrained men...
誰會想到一群沒經驗的人
...would do so well against  such a considerable adversary?
會把波斯大軍打得落花流水
We're going to need all of our strength  for tomorrow's fight.
我們需要所有精力應付明天戰役
How long do you think we can hold them?
你覺得我們能抵擋多久？
If my plan is to work...
如果我的計劃成功
...long enough for the Spartans  to unite Greece.
會撐到斯巴達加入希臘為止
Men!
弟兄們
Who will share their wine with me?
誰要陪我喝一杯？
Report.
回報狀況
We are still tallying the losses.
我們還在統計損傷
But you must understand,  it is extremely difficult...
請諒解，海象和天色…
...given the sea and the darkness...
讓情況棘手
...to get an accurate--
很難精確統計…
Report?
回報狀況
Seventy-five ships lost.
損失75艘船
Thirty damaged beyond repair.
30艘無法修復
Twenty could return with a few weeks' work  in a safe harbor.
20艘在安全港口  修補後可再參戰
The commander of the Greek force  is named Themistokles.
那位希臘統帥名叫帝米斯托克力
Yes, he is an Athenian general.
是的，他是位雅典將軍
He's rumored to have loosed the arrow...
據說就是他放箭…
...that felled the great King Darius himself.
殺了吾王大流士
No!
不
This Themistokles has shown himself  to be quite brilliant in battle.
這個帝米斯托克力顯然  是位傑出戰士
Which is more than I can say for any of you.
這勝過我對你們所有人的評價
Do you gentlemen find my command  unreasonable?
各位覺得我的要求不合理嗎？
Is it too much to ask for victory?
想要獲勝太貪心了嗎？
Your disappointment in yesterday's losses...  ...is warranted.
您對昨日戰敗的失望可以理解
My disappointment.
我的失望
My disappointment is not with my losses.
我失望的不是戰敗
The meager number of damaged ships  and dead slaves means nothing to me.
區區幾艘破船和死了幾個奴隸  對我毫無意義
No, my disappointment...
不，我的失望
...is in these men.
是對你們這些人
For though I stand...
因為我身處…
...among 10,000...
一萬將士之中
...I am alone.
卻還是孤獨一人
I long for a soul  who would stand by my side.
我渴望一個和我並肩作戰
Who I could trust.
值得信任之人
Tell me, General Kashani.
告訴我，卡沙尼將軍
Are you that man?
你是那個人嗎？
You will taste your victory by the day's end.
今日終了時，您會品嚐勝利滋味
I will make certain of it.
我會確保這點
I hope so.
希望如此
Advance!
推進
NOW!
現在
Don't lose sight of them.
別追丟了
The Greeks are retreating.  He's got him right where he wants him.
- 希臘人撒退了  - 這正中他的下懷
Kashani is a fine tactician.
卡沙尼用兵如神
I was speaking of Themistokles.
我說的是帝米斯托克力
Rocks!
岩石
Stop, stop!
停，快停
Stop!
停下來
Brace yourselves!
大家抓緊船身
What are you doing here?
你在這裏幹嘛？
A man's responsibility  is to protect his family and his nation.
一個男人有責任捍衛家人和國家
- Who told you this?  - My father.
- 這是誰說的？  - 我父親
You see how Themistokles  employs deception with such grace?
看到帝米斯托克力  如何巧妙地引君入甕嗎？
- Why is it so much to ask for victory?  - How can I make amends?
- 要求戰勝怎麼就這麼難呢？  - 我如何能彌補？
Silence.
閉嘴
You will carry a message for me.
你去替我傳個口信
Now they will fear us!
現在他們怕了
Now they will fear  the Greek men-at-arms! Hup!
現在他們會敬畏希臘戰士了
He's right.
他說得對
Fear the Greek fighting man.
要對希臘戰士戒慎恐懼
Fear his sword.
敬畏他的劍
His shield.
他的盾
Fear his love for Mother Greece.
敬畏他對母國希臘的愛
But most of all...
但最重要的是
...fear his freedom!
敬畏他的自由
對
Don't be angry with the boy.
別生孩子的氣
I took him under my command.
我將他納入我麾下
Anger is something I reserve  for my enemies.
我只對敵人生氣
Themistokles.
帝米斯托克力
Artemisia's ship is being anchored  in neutral waters.
雅特米西亞的船停泊在中立水域
She'd like to meet with Themistokles.
她想邀帝米斯托克力會面
- How can you guarantee his safe return?  - Well, boy...
如何確保他安全返回？  小子
...the only honor for her now...
她想雪恥的方式
...will be when she watches  your crushed and broken fleet...
是看著你們破碎的艦隊…
...sinking to the bottom of the Aegean...
沉沒在愛琴海
...and is able to recognize you...
還要看到你…
...nailed to the mast of your ship  with her sword...
被她用劍釘在你桅桿上
...as you descend to a watery grave.
再隨著你的船葬身海底
Why didn't you just say that to begin with?
你怎麼不早說呢？
Welcome to my humble barge.
歡迎來到我的小船
We are honored by your presence.
我們因您大駕光臨深感榮幸
Your barge and you...
你的小船和你…
...are quite impressive.
都令人驚艷
Kind words.
您客套了
Now come, Themistokles.  We have much to discuss.
來吧，帝米斯托克力  我們有很多要談的
Do you believe the Greeks  are descended from the gods?
你相信希臘人是諸神的後裔？
I have heard some say that.
我聽過這種說法
And what of you?  ls there a god in your lineage?
那你呢？族譜中有神嗎？
My men say so, and based on  the last two days' battle...
我的手下認為如此  加上過去兩天的戰況
...I'd say there's a spark of the divine in you.
我會說你的確天縱英才
Now who's using kind words?
現在是誰客套了？
My men also say that it was you...
聽說是你…
...who slayed the good King Darius  at Marathon.
在馬拉松之戰時  殺了大流士國王
Many heroic deeds occurred on that day.
那天發生許多英雄事跡
But it was 10 years ago...
但畢竟是十年前
...and the facts of battle  are often embellished.
而戰爭史實常被誇大
This deed, you would remember.
這種功業想必會記得
I do what I must to defend Greece.
為了捍衛希臘，我願赴湯蹈火
And I do what I must to defeat her.
為了擊敗希臘，我也願意
For every one Greek killed,  you must kill a thousand Persians.
每一個希臘士兵陣亡  你就得殺一千個波斯士兵
For every ship I sink...
我每擊沉一艘船
...you must sink a hundred.
你就得擊沉一百艘
I can sustain losses for weeks.
我頂得住數周戰敗
Months, if need be.
如果必要，數月也行
My numbers will defeat you...
我會用人海戰術打垮你
...and I will take your precious boats  with my sword.
我會用劍摧毀你珍愛的艦隊
I will take your Greek freedom.
我會踐踏希臘的自由
Are you asking me  to negotiate a surrender?
你想跟我談招降條件嗎？
No.
不
I offer you a chance  to avoid such misery and join me.
我給你機會免除痛苦  並讓你加入我
I'm in need of a commander such as you.
我需要像你這樣的領導人才
Look at the defense you've mounted.
看你建立的防禦戰線
A handful of triremes.
幾艘三列槳船
Leonidas with 300 Spartans.
雷奧尼達和三百名斯巴達士兵
It's insulting, frankly...
這樣應付…
...that the mightiest empire the world  has ever seen is met by this.
史上最強的帝國  也未免太污辱人了
I don't blame you, Themistokles.
我不怪你，帝米斯托克力
You fought as if the blood  of Poseidon himself...
你驍勇善戰…
...was coursing through your veins.
宛如海神轉世
No, I blame Greece.
不，我怪罪的是希臘
The squabbling bureaucrats  protecting their political hides...
那些吵鬧不休的政客為了自保
...by sending you here to die.
讓你來此送死
And yet you still fight.
但你仍然奮戰不懈
So there must be...
所以一定有…
What?
什麼？
Family back home in Athens  that compels you...
在雅典的一家大小  那迫使你…
...to battle with such passion?
如此熱切的奮戰？
Truth is, I've had no time for family.
老實說，我無暇經營家庭
I have spent my entire adult life...
我成年就將身心奉獻…
...with my one true love...
給唯一摯愛
...the Greek fleet...
希臘海軍
...and my one passion...
我唯一目標
...readying it for you.
就是準備迎戰你
Now, that brings me pleasure...
那真讓我開心
...the thought of you pining away for me...
想到你全心全意為我準備
...forsaking family and love...
放棄家庭和愛情
...for the promise of a deeper ecstasy.
為的是更嚮往無法自拔的迷戀
The ecstasy of steel and flesh...
鋼鐵和血肉之軀的快感
...death and life...
死亡與存活
...of rage...
慾望中…
...and sweat of muscle...
汗水淋漓的肌肉
...of pure joy...
最純粹的喜悅
...and deepest sorrow.
和最深沉的哀愁
Die with me each night and be born again  with me each morning...
每晚和我一同死去  早晨再一起重生
...as you plant your sword  into the hearts of our enemies.
將你的劍刺向我們敵人的心中
You fight for freedom.
你為自由而戰
I offer freedom without  consequence or responsibility.
我提供你不計後果  沒有責任義務的自由
Join me...
加入我
...at my side.
在我身旁
Breathe each breath with me  as if it were your last.
和我一起呼吸  彷彿那是你最後一口氣
Join me.
加入我
No.
不
You're no god. You're just a man.
你不是神  你只是凡人
Be quick with your sword.
下手快一點
You'll not have your death tonight.
今晚還不是你的死期
Guards!
侍衛
Remove this filth from my ship.
把這個下三濫趕下船
Well?
怎麼？
What have you learned?
有什麼發現？
Can Artemisia be beaten?
有辦法打敗雅特米西亞嗎？
The next time that we face her...
我們下次和她短兵相見時
...she's going to bring all of hell with her.
她會打開地獄大門
Hold! Hold!
抓緊船身，謹守位置
Send in my personal guard.
釋出我的私人侍衛
Pull back!
退後
Retreat!
撒退
- Retreat!  - Retreat!
- 撤退  - 撤退
Themistokles!
帝米斯托克力
In the water!
在水中
Archers on deck now!
弓箭手，快上甲板
Archers on deck now! Quickly!
弓箭手立刻上甲板來
Starboard side!
右舷
Fire at will!
全力放箭
Fight on, boy.
繼續奮戰，孩子
Uh-huh.
Fight on!
繼續奮戰
Aim for the men on top!
瞄準上面的人
UP there!
最上面
Abandon ship! Abandon ship!
- 棄船  - 棄船
Abandon ship!
棄船
快逃
The dead have no guilt.
已死之人無須面對愧疚
No responsibility.
無須擔負責任
Themistokles watches the bodies  of his men...
帝米斯托克力看著弟兄…
...turn the Aegean red with blood.
將愛琴海染成一片血紅
Were they sacrificed for his ego?
他們是否因他的自大而喪命？
Or to relieve the guilt of the long-ago  mistake at Marathon?
或是為了平反他多年前  在馬拉松犯下的錯誤？
How many men would have been saved...
若他多年前殺了王子
...if Themistokles had killed that boy?
多少弟兄能免於一死？
Not even his own soul can be sure.
就算他的靈魂也無法回答
My friend.
我的朋友
We faced the odds.
我們以小搏大
Together.
同心協力
Listen to me...
聽我說
...Themistokles.
帝米斯托克力
You will have to fight...
明天早上
...with twice as much strength  in the morning.
你得加倍猛攻
We will fight shoulder-to-shoulder.
我們一起並肩作戰
No, my son.
不，兒子
You will carry on for both of us.
你得替我倆保家衛國
What did he say?
他說了什麼？
I will tell you in time, boy.
將來我再告訴你，孩子
Quiet now.
先默哀吧
You go and be with your father's spirit.
守候你父親的靈魂
How many times do you think  we will repeat such a tragedy?
我們還得面對多少這種悲劇？
As many times as we must.
該面對就面對
We are turning young men into memories.
我們將年輕人變成明日黃花
Do you think I enjoy this?
你以為我喜歡這樣？
Witnessing my friend's final breath?
看著我的朋友嚥氣？
Every widow that is made by my decision...
每個因我決定而喪夫的寡婦
...every child that will grow  without a father...
每個因喪父獨立成長的孩子
...they are my choices.
這些都是我做的選擇
This is the burden of my command.
這就是領袖的重擔
How easy it is to silence...
最精銳和堅毅的…
...the strong and self-disciplined.
兵團也不過如此
Let my army witness  the great warriors of Sparta.
讓我大軍見識偉大的斯巴達戰士
March them past these corpses.
沿著這些屍首行軍
Let them see the cost  of daring to challenge the god-king.
讓他們知道忤逆神王的下場
King Leonidas...
雷奧尼達國王…
...and his brave 300  were the finest Greece has to offer.
和他的三百壯士  是希臘所能動員的最精英攻勢
There will be no saviors...
不會再有人…
...to rise up and vanquish us.
能起身抗衡
Nothing will stop the march of my empire.
無人能阻止我帝國的邁進
Your Majesty.
大王
You, take this dead king's sword...
你，把死去國王的劍…
...to Athens.
送去雅典
Let them know  that I am coming next for them.
讓他們知道我大軍已壓境
Let them know...
讓他們知道
...Athens...
雅典
...their prize jewel of a city...
他們最珍視的城市
...will disappear from the histories.
會消失在歷史中
Themistokles!
帝米斯托克力
I bring word...
我帶來…
...from Thermopylae.  Leonidas was betrayed by a hunchback.
溫泉關噩耗  雷奧尼達被駝子出賣了
The Spartans have been slaughtered.
斯巴達壯士慘遭屠殺
The Hot Gates have fallen.
溫泉關失守了
Such a sacrifice.
如此慘重的犧牲
Now Greece has her martyrs.
現在希臘有從容赴義的烈士了
Daxos, take that message...
戴索斯
...from the Hot Gates...
將溫泉關失守的消息
...to every city, every village.
帶往每個城鎮及鄉村
Let every countryman hear your words.
讓每個希臘人都知道
But they are dead. All of them.
但他們死了，全死光了
Sparta's sacrifice will be what unites us.
斯巴達的犧牲會促進我們團結
Now go.
去吧
Hyah!
Move all of our ships and men back  to the safety of Salamis.
將船艦和弟兄移師薩拉米斯
And you?
那你呢？
I will take Daxos' message to Athens.
我會將戴索斯的信息帶回雅典
I was told a hunchback  was accountable for the fall of the Hot Gates.
我聽說溫泉關因為一個駝子失守
That he sold out his country...
他出賣國家
...pulled the crimson from his back  and replaced it with Persian gold.
背棄身上的紅披風  只為了波斯賞金
What is your name, traitor?
你叫什麼名字，叛徒？
Ephialtes of Trachis.
特拉基斯的厄菲阿爾特
I should wet this noble blade  with your blood.
我應該用你血洗這把尊貴的劍
You would be right to do so.
你有權如此
There is little beauty about me.
我的確自慚形穢
There is little beauty in what I have done.
我的所作所為令人髮指
Say what you must.
有話快說
I beg of you...
我求求你
...and all of Athens!
還有全體雅典市民
The god-king will burn this city  to the ground!
神王會放火焚城
What does he mean?
他是什麼意思？
Quiet yourselves!
安靜
Leonidas' and Sparta's great sacrifice  was no defeat.
雷奧尼達和斯巴達的壯烈犧牲  不代表失敗
It was a beautiful victory.
而是美麗的榮耀
This simple act of valor...
這個象徵英勇的義行
...will allow us to rally each  of our city-states...
會鼓舞希臘各城邦
...and unite Greece...
並促使團結
...for one purpose...
只為一個目的
...against one enemy!
對抗同一外侮
And you.
而你
You take this message to your god-king.
把這信息帶給你的神王
That we will take whatever ships  we have left...
我們會集合剩餘船艦
...and finish this in the Bay of Salamis.
在薩拉米斯灣決一死戰
But there will be death and destruction.
但這樣會死傷慘重
Yes, there will be.
沒錯，的確如此
Themistokles.
帝米斯托克力
I'm here to speak to your queen.
我來此求見女王
A warning, Athenian.
我先警告你，雅典人
You may not receive a warm welcome.
你不會受到熱烈歡迎
May I offer my deepest sympathies.
請容我致上最深哀悼
I cannot change what has happened  to Leonidas...
我無法改變雷奧尼達的事
...but his sacrifice will not be forgotten.
但他的犧牲不會被遺忘
Do not lecture me on sacrifice,  and be quick with your words, Athenian.
別跟我談犧牲  有話快說，雅典人
I request of you the entire Spartan navy.
我想借斯巴達海軍一用
Every man, every ship...
請提供你所有的…
-...that you can spare.  - Have I not given enough...
- 人力和船艦  - 為你一統希臘的美夢…
...for your dream of a united Greece?
我犧牲還不夠嗎？
Shall I put swords in the hands  of my son? Our children?
難道要讓兒子持劍？  送孩子上戰場？
Would that please you?
那樣你才滿意嗎？
Have I not given enough  for your ambitions, Themistokles?
我為你的野心犧牲得還不夠嗎？  帝米斯托克力
A king.
一個國王
Husbands, fathers, brothers.
丈夫、父親、兄弟
Sparta will give no more.
斯巴達不再任你予取予求
This belongs with you.
這屬於你
Avenge him.
替他復仇
The Oracle's words stood as a warning.
先知早就發出警語
All of Greece will fall...
希臘會全軍覆滅
...as Persian fire reduces Athens to cinder.
波斯烈焰會將雅典城燒成灰燼
For Athens is a pile of stone and wood...
畢竟雅典只是由木石…
...and cloth and dust...
及塵土搭建
...and, as dust, will vanish into the wind.
而塵土終將灰飛煙滅
Only the Athenians themselves exist.
最終留下的只有雅典人民
And the fate of the world  hangs on their every syllable.
世界的命運  懸在雅典議會的最終決議
Only the Athenians exist.
最終留下的只有雅典人
And only stout wooden ships can save them.
唯有強健的艦隊才能拯救他們
Wooden ships...
木製的軍艦
...and a tidal wave of heroes' blood.
還有英雄熱血捲起的驚濤．駭浪
The Greeks were fools to stand against us.
希臘人選擇抵抗真是愚蠢
Leonidas and his pride...
雷奧尼達和他的傲氣
...were no match for the will of a god.
也無法與神王的意志相抗衡
Themistokles was a worthless coward.
帝米斯托克力是個無用的懦夫
And now...
而現在
...this pathetic navy  is barely worth our attention.
這支可悲海軍幾乎不值得注意
If that worthless coward  had stood at my side...
要是那個無用的懦夫  願意臣服我麾下
...we would have laid the world...
我們可以為你…
...at your feet.
拿下全世界
My king.
吾王
Your humble servant brings you news.
您忠誠的僕人給您送口信來了
The Greek fleet are defenseless...
希臘艦隊聚集在薩拉米斯灣
...within the Bay of Salamis.
殘破不堪一擊
You need only finish them.
您不費吹灰之力便可解決
Who commands their forces?
統帥是誰？
Themistokles of Athens.
雅典城的帝米斯托克力
Themistokles is dead.
帝米斯托克力死了
He is alive. I have seen him myself.
他還活著，我才親眼見過
Ready my troops and armor.
備好軍隊和盔甲
We will attack at once.
我們一舉出擊
Wisdom...
明智之舉是…
...would have us...
先派人…
...send a probing force to confirm  it is not a trap.
探虛實，確保不是陷阱
You would dare to advise me  in matters of war?
憑你也配指點我戰術？
I am the god-king.
我是神王
I am the one who triumphed over Leonidas.
是我大舉戰勝雷奧尼達
I am the one who laid waste...
是我將繁華的雅典…
...to this showpiece of Athens.
夷為平地
- I am your king.  - Killing Leonidas and his men...
- 我是你的王  - 殺死雷奧尼達和他手下
...only made them martyrs.
只讓他們成為烈士
And when you razed Athens...
當你摧毀雅典
...you set fire to the only thing...
也把這國家…
...of value in this country.
唯一的價值燒光了
I will attack the Greeks...
我會結集所有海軍
...with my entire navy.
攻擊希臘
Artemisia.
雅特米西亞
Enough!
夠了
Do not forget who put the crown  on your childish head.
別忘了是誰讓你這小子戴穩王冠
My king.
吾王
Now sit on your golden throne...
你就乖乖坐在金殿上
...and watch this battle  from the safety I provide you.
看我出征維護你安全吧
There in the distance...
我們在遠處
...we witness the destruction of Athens.
見證雅典城毀人亡
Alone, we will face the monster  that cast a shadow across our land.
我們得獨自面對侵略家園的巨獸
I had prayed that the Spartans  would come to lend a hand this morning.
我祈禱斯巴達今早會出兵相救
Perhaps they feel they have given enough.
或許他們覺得已犧牲夠了
You failed us all.
你辜負了大家
This is your fault, Themistokles.
都是你的錯，帝米斯托克力
Without Spartans, we're farmhands.
少了斯巴達，我們只是群農夫
We should've negotiated  with the Persians when we had the chance.
當初還有機會時…
早該與波斯談和
You are all right.
你們說得都對
Yes, we are down to a handful of boats.
是的，我們只剩幾艘船
And, yes, we are just farmhands.
是的，我們只是一群農夫
We are tradesmen.
一群販夫走卒
We are boys...
一群男孩
...turned to men through the sacrifice  and forge of combat.
被戰爭的犧牲和殘酷鍛煉成人
I played a dangerous game...
我走了一步險棋
...and I lost!
結果輸了
If you choose to turn your back on me...
如果你們選擇背棄我
...on your country...
背棄國家
...I will not judge you.
我也沒有異議
You are free to leave.
你們有離開的自由
You are still free men.
你們目前還是自由之人
Very well.
很好
Then let us...
那就讓我們…
...put our shoulders to work  and free those ships from the bosom of Greece.
並肩協力  摧毀在希臘懷中作亂的敵艦
Today is a privilege to call our own.
我們今日有幸在此
A story that will be told  for a thousand years.
寫下一個將被傳頌千世的故事
Let our final stand...
讓我們的最後一役
...be recorded to the histories.
被記入青史中
And let it be shown...
讓大家知道
...that we chose to die on our feet...
我們寧願挺身受死
...rather than live on our knees!
也不願屈膝茍活
There is only one thing  you need to know today.
你今天只需知道一件事
Not to get killed.
不要陣亡
No. Your father's last words.
不，你父親的遺言
He told me that you had earned  the right to sit at the table.
他說你已贏得  和大家平起平坐的權利
Well, my brother,  I have no more tactics or tricks.
兄弟，我已千機用盡
This will be the last battle that we share.
這將是最後一次一起奮戰
We have fought next to one other  for as long as I can remember.
從有記憶以來  我們就一直並肩奮戰
Nothing would please me more  than to rest this sword.
我最大的願望就是卸甲封刀
- The preparations that are required?  - Below deck.
- 我要你準備的東西？  - 在甲板底下
- Good.  - Are you sure...
- 很好  - 你確定…
...that you want to commit everything?
要如此孤注一擲？
Yes.
是的
Without Artemisia's command,  the Persian navy is nothing.
沒有雅特米西亞發號施令  波斯海軍不足畏懼
We will never be able to reach her.
我們永遠無法接近她
I will reach her...
我會獨自前往
...and put an end to this.
了結這件事
There will be no room for a retreat.
你將置身險境，沒有退路
I know.
我知道
Today the last Greek ships will be destroyed.
今日我們要徹底終結希臘艦隊
Show them no mercy.
務必斬盡殺絕
Give them no quarter.
不留任何活路
Today we will dance across the backs  of dead Greeks.
今日我們將在希臘屍首上歡慶
Today we deliver submission.
今日我們要迫使他們屈膝稱臣
Today I want to feel Themistokles' throat...
今日我要將帝米斯托克力的脖子…
...beneath my boots.
踩在腳下
Men, brace yourselves!
弟兄們，抓緊船身
Prepare for close quarters.
準備近身搏擊
Attack!
攻擊
Your father watches you!
你父親與你同在
Hold nothing back!
全力以赴
Seize your glory!
爭取榮耀
I'm not here as a witness.
我不是來這裏觀戰的
NOW!
現在
And let them send our souls straight to hell!
讓我們在地獄同歸於盡
Hyah! Come on!
快點
You offered freedom without...
你願提供我不計後果
-...consequence or responsibility.  - Are you accepting my offer?
- 沒有責任義務的自由？  - 你接受我的邀約嗎？
My answer is still no.
我的答案仍然不變
You fight much harder than you fuck.
你作戰可比做愛賣力多了
Surrender to me or meet your death.
向我稱臣，或是受死
Who would you fight...
少了我…
...if not for me?
誰能與你匹敵？
No one could challenge your skill.
沒人是你的敵手
I would rather die a free man than as a slave.
我寧願自由死去  也不願淪為奴隸
Even if the chain was attached to you.
即便主子是你
It begins as a whisper.
開始時只是傳聞
A promise.
一個承諾
The lightest of breezes...
一股清風…
...dances through the rigging...
輕拂船纜
...as it creaks above the death cries  of 10,000 men.
掠過萬名壯士的死前怒號
It moves through her hair  as gently as a lover's hand.
就像愛人的手，輕柔穿越髮梢
That breeze...
那股清風
...that promise, became a wind,  a wind that is blown across Greece...
那個承諾幻化成風潮  這股風潮席捲全希臘
...carrying a message told again and again...
傳遞自由女神…
...of our Lady Freedom  and how wise she was...
反覆傳頌的理念
...to charge Leonidas to lay all at her feet.
以及她讓雷奧尼達  壯烈犧牲的智慧
A wind, my brothers, of sacrifice.
我的弟兄們，那是犧牲的風潮
A wind of freedom.
自由的風潮
A wind of justice.
正義的風潮
A wind of vengeance.
復仇的風潮
Ah-ooh! Ah-ooh! Ah-ooh!
You are being surrounded.
你被包圍了
All of Greece has united against you.
希臘上下已聯合起來對抗你
Delphi, Thebes, Olympia...
德爾菲、底比斯  奧林匹亞
...Arcadia and Sparta.
阿卡迪亞  還有斯巴達
If death comes for me today, I'm ready.
若今日是我死期，我已準備上路
I could lower my sword.
我也可以放下劍
There's still time for you  to ready a launch and escape.
你還有時間乘船逃走
It would be a poor choice  to force my hand into action.
別逼我非殺你不可
Now order your ships to disengage  and surrender to me.
命令你的艦隊停戰並向我投降
Surrender?
投降？
導演：諾姆穆洛
編劇：柴克史耐德  寇特約翰史泰
製片：吉安尼奴納利  馬克坎頓
製片：柴克史耐德  黛博拉史耐德
製片：柏尼高德曼
漫畫原著：法蘭克米勒
主演：蘇利文斯坦布萊頓
主演：伊娃葛蓮
主演：琳娜海迪
主演：漢斯麥瑟遜
主演：考倫穆維
主演：大衛溫翰
主演：羅德林哥桑特羅
主演：傑克歐康諾  安德魯提納曼
主演：依高納爾  安德魯普烈文
片名：300壯士：帝國崛起